Social History of Spencer, Indiana 1974-1975 ohrc092
Center for Documentary Research and Practice
Social History of Spencer, Indiana
1974-1976
Center for Documentary Research and Practice
Indiana University Center for the Study of History and Memory
ohrc092
55 Interviews Audio files, transcripts, and collateral materials
This project interviews people living in Spencer, Indiana. The interviewees include a variety of ages and the time period of their experiences span the 1910s-1970s. The interviews include discussion of small town life and changes throughout the past sixty years. The education system, religious beliefs, and economic conditions of the town and surrounding county are discussed. Many interviewees discuss the Great Depression and its effect on the business owners and farmers of the area. Changing moral standards and generational differences are themes throughout the project.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains fifty-five interviews conducted over two years. The interviews range from 25 to 145 minutes. All interviews consist of audio tapes and most have typed transcripts.
Acquisition Information
Oral history interviews conducted by the Indiana University Center for the Study of History and Memory from 1968 to the present, with particular focus on the history of twentieth-century America and the Midwest.
- Allen, Jessie, December 1974; 75-044; Crouch, Tamara; 17 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 40 minutes; no index
  Access Status
  Open
  Scope and Content Note
  Jessie Allen, born 1889 and died 1978, moved with her family to Owen County in 1900. She speaks briefly about her childhood and attending school in Spencer before going into some detail about living in the community during the Great Depression. She also discusses the decline in business and overall friendliness since she moved to Spencer.
  McCormick's Creek State Park, Indiana; Morgan County, Indiana; Owen County, Indiana; church events; Great Depression; local business decline; racial diversity; religious beliefs; Spencer public schools
- Alspaugh, Effie, October 17, 1974; 74-004; Brown, Mike; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 30 minutes
  Effie Alspaugh discusses the local history of Spencer, Indiana.
  Spencer, Indiana; local history
- Bain, Chic; Bain, Irene, April 7, 1975; 75-037; Noland, Craig; 47 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 115 minutes; no index
  Chic and Irene Bain, both born 1903, speak about their education and growing up in a small town. They discuss their belief that mothers working outside the home was one of the worst things to happen for children's morals and schools. They also speak about the time it took for Chic to become accepted in the community, and the way the community treated the rich and poor.
  Bloomington, Indiana; Martinsville, Indiana; economic class differences; educational system; Great Depression; racial diversity; religious beliefs; Spencer public schools; working mothers; Scott, Derby
- Bowen, Eloise; Bowen, Gene, March 6, 1975; 75-038; Brown, Mike; Perry, Robert; Not transcribed, 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 65 minutes
  Gene and Eloise Bowen discuss religious beliefs and schools in Spencer, Indiana.
  religious beliefs; Spencer public schools
- Bowler, Ollie, March 17, 1975; 75-041; Hatfield, David; Noland, Craig; 28 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 65 minutes; no index
  Ollie Bowler, born 1901, moved to Spencer during the Great Depression. He discusses the influence of politics and the wealthy in the community, especially in regards to policies and employment. He also speaks about the friendliness of the community and how businesses have declined since he first moved to the town.
  community pride; crime rates; Great Depression; local politics; racial diversity; religious beliefs; police; Owen County Welfare Board; Works Progress Administration
- Bryant, Gary, April 15, 1975; 76-008; Crouch, Tamara; Hatfield, David; 18 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 45 minutes; no index
  Gary Bryant, born 1934 and died 1995, grew up in Spencer and lived there most of his life. He speaks about the large number of people living in town who must commute to work everyday, and the need to travel to larger cities to shop. He also briefly touches on the town's clannishness and how it reacts to newcomers.
  Indianapolis, Indiana; child discipline; commuting; education changes; local employment
- Buker, Watson, December 5, 1974; 75-006; Hatfield, David; Noland, Craig; 44 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 105 minutes; no index
  Watson Buker, born 1915, lived most of his adult life in Spencer. He speaks about the influence of religion in his life and, as school board president, the value of education. Without giving too many details, he discusses the firing of the high school principal over differences in ideology.
  school board president; Owen County, Indiana; African-American population; church activities; Church of the Nazarene; commuting; Education; local politics; religious beliefs; small town advantages; Spencer public schools; World War II; Fraternal Order of Masons; Improved Order of Redmen; Spencer Elementary School
- Camden, Rose, October 26, 1974; 74-018; Crouch, Tamara; Hatfield, David; 18 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 45 minutes; no index
  Rose Camden speaks about life in Greene County and Spencer, Indiana. She discusses the differences in education, particularly discipline, between her generation and the present. She also discusses the importance of religion as well as the denominational friction between the churches in town. She speaks about crime, the bank robbery in the 1920s, and the differences between the economic classes.
  Greene County, Indiana; Lyons, Indiana; Spencer, Indiana; bank robbery; Church of Christ; crime rates; economic class differences; education changes; Great Depression; religious beliefs; religious denominations; Spencer public schools; Riley, James Whitcomb, 1849-1916
- Clark, James W., June 18, 1975; 75-070; Brown, Mike; 12 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 30 minutes; no index
  James W. Clark, born 1891, speaks about his education and religion, including how it has evolved over the years. He has also been involved in the local politics, such as county clerk and school board, and speaks about the changes in local politics from mostly Democratic to Republican.
  Education; Great Depression; local employment; local politics; religious beliefs; Spencer public schools; Wesleyan church; Spencer-Owen County School Board
- Clark, James; Long, Rosalie; Long, Janet; Monroe, Sandra; Monroe, Dortha, April 8, 1975; 75-035; Hatfield, David; Noland, Craig; Crouch, Tamara; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 78 minutes
  James Clark, Janet Long, Rosalie Long, Dortha Monroe, and Sandra Monroe speak about local history, education, religion, social classes, and economic changes in Spencer, Indiana.
  Owen County, Indiana; economic class differences; Education; local history; religious beliefs
- Close, Roscoe, March 20. 1975; 75-049; Perry, Robert; 37 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 90 minutes; no index
  Roscoe Close, born 1914, grew up in the Spencer area and speaks about his early history, including school, trapping, and farming. He also talks about education and discipline in the school as well as community interaction between the rich and poor.
  Spencer, Indiana; Catholicism; child discipline; Education; farming; one-room schools; religious beliefs; trapping; Peden, Walter
- Crouch, Louis D., November 7, 1974; December 14, 1974; 74-023; Brown, Mike; Not transcribed, 2 tapes, 150 minutes
  Louis Crouch speaks about religion and education in Spencer, Indiana
  Owen County, Indiana; church activities; Education; local history; religious beliefs
- Curtis, Jessie; Hight, Ina Mae Wendell; Hight, John R.; Laymon, Gladys; Peden, Donna; Weymouth, Martha, October 24, 1974; 74-005; Hatfield, David; Noland, Craig; 49 pages; 2 tapes, 3 3/4 ips, 120 minutes; no index
  Jessie Curtis, Ina Hight, Gladys Laymon, Donna Peden, and Martha Weymouth speak about life in Spencer during the early twentieth century. They discuss both their family and local history, education, and religion. They also talk about the community interaction, such as that between the rich and poor, and the recreational events.
  Gosport, Indiana; McCormick's Creek, Indiana; Quincy, Indiana; bank failures; child discipline; education changes; farm life; Great Depression; local history; racial diversity; religious beliefs; Indiana University; World Products Company; Campbell, Harley; Peden, Thomas Alexander; Scott, Derby
- Dyer, Lillian, December 5, 1974; 75-005; Hatfield, David; 34 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 80 minutes; no index
  Lillian Dyer, born 1906, was a music teacher in Spencer, Indiana. She discusses her knowledge of the community, and her thoughts about religion and education.
  Owen County, Indiana; Spencer, Indiana; music teacher; Education; Great Depression; racial diversity; religious beliefs
- Edwards, Charles, 1975; 76-062; Brown, Mike; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 65 minutes
  Charles Edwards speaks about local history and his involvement in Indiana politics.
  Owen County, Indiana; local history; local politics
- Emerson, Violet, April 3, 1975; 75-075; Fenton, Leslie; 16 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 40 minutes; no index
  Violet Emerson has lived in Spencer since her husband opened a drugstore during the Great Depression in the nineteen thirties. She speaks about her early childhood, including the sense of importance of education and religion she got from her parents. In fact, her father apparently moved to Bloomington when they were younger to prepare them for college. She speaks about life in Spencer after the 1930s, and especially discusses the importance of religion and the commute of those seeking employment.
  Bloomington, Indiana; Owen County, Indiana; child discipline; education changes; local employment; local politics; religious beliefs; Emerson Drugstore; Rexall Drugstore
- Fisher, Nelson, August 29, 1975; 75-077; Brown, Mike; 20 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 50 minutes; no index
  Nelson Fisher was born June 4, 1889 and lived his whole life in Spencer, Indiana. He quit high school at the age of eighteen, although he was only in the ninth grade, due to a series of illnesses that kept him out of school for a long period of time. He went to work for the Pennsylvania Railroad in Spencer and became a telegraph operator. He discusses his success at his job because he was ambidextrous, being born left-handed and trained to be right-handed in school. In the 1930s, Mr. Fisher had to retire because tuberculosis had settled in his bones. He has lived ever since on his railroad pension and Social Security. Mr. Nelson also talks about his children, his time spent in various nursing homes over the years, and his religious beliefs.
  telegraph operator; Florida; bank robbery; Church of Christ; disability; funeral services; nuclear power; nursing homes; pensions; railroad decline; religious beliefs; tuberculosis; Pennsylvania Railroad
- Fulford, James, April 16, 1975; 76-007; Noland, Craig; 20 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 50 minutes; no index
  James Fulford, born in La Porte County, Indiana November 12, 1924, was the principal of Owen Valley High School at the time of the interview. He was raised in Monroe County, and attended Indiana University to get a teaching degree. Mr. Fulford taught many places in the state of Indiana, and was brought to Owen County to assist in the county's school consolidation plans. He compares the educational system that was in place when he was growing up to the present. He discusses the challenges of school consolidation. He talks about child discipline in the past and today. Finally, Mr. Fulford discusses Spencer's religious communities, consisting of many small churches of different denominations.
  high school teacher; school principal; Bloomington, Indiana; Coal City, Indiana; Gosport, Indiana; La Porte, Indiana; Patricksburg, Indiana; Peru, Indiana; Stinesville, Indiana; 1944 GI Bill; child discipline; local religious communities; religious beliefs; school consolidation; World War II; Indiana University; Owen County Ministerial Association; Owen Valley High School; Stinesville High School
- Goldberg, Isabella, February 26, 1975; 75-064; Noland, Greg; Perry, Robert; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips
  Isabella Goldberg discusses life in Spencer, Indiana.
  local history
- Gross, Raymond, December 7, 1974; 75-011; Crouch, Tamara; Perry, Robert; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 120 minutes
  Raymond Gross discusses life in Spencer, Indiana during the Great Depression and the local history of the area.
  Great Depression; local history
- Hackworthy, John, February 26, 1975; 76-009; Brown, Mike; Hatfield, David; 24 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 60 minutes; no index
  John Hackworthy, a a small business owner, discusses the changes in Spencer, Indiana since he and his wife moved there in 1964. He talks about school consolidation and compares the schools in Wisconsin, his native state, to those in Owen County. He talks about the Spencer, Indiana Catholic community, of which he is a member. Mr. Hackworthy compares the atmosphere of the small Spencer community to that of larger communities in Wisconsin.
  small business owner; Wisconsin; Catholicism; child discipline; local scandal; racial discrimination; religious discrimination; school consolidation; Owen Valley High School; Spencer Chamber of Commerce; Stella Products
- Hickam, Elliott, February 7, 1975; 75-048; Hatfield, David; Noland, Greg; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 80 minutes
  Elliott Hickam discusses the local history of Spencer, Indiana, small town life, and the Spencer educational system.
  economic class differences; local history; small town life
- Hickam, Willis, October 3, 1974; 74-008; Hatfield, David; 20 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 50 minutes; no index; photograph of interviewee
  Willis Hickam has lived in Spencer, Indiana his entire life. He graduated from Spencer High School in the 1910s and attended Indiana University to earn a law degree to follow in his father's footsteps. He then returned to Spencer to practice law. Mr. Hickam discusses the changes in the small town over the years. He talks about how Spencer fared in the Great Depression and how Spencer fared. He speaks of the differences in the economic classes in Spencer and how they react to each other. He discusses Spencer's religious communities, how they relate to each other, and how they have changed over the years. Mr. Hickam also mentions some memories of his life in Spencer, especially a bank robbery that occurred in 1924.
  attorney; Bloomington, Indiana; bank robbery; child discipline; divorce; Great Depression; local history; local politics; local religious communities; small town life; town square
- Honeay, John S., October 31, 1974; 74-019; Hatfield, David; Noland, Craig; 60 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 85 minutes; no index
  John S. Honeay, a Baptist pastor in Spencer, Indiana, was born in Colorado, but grew up in Monrovia, Indiana in Morgan County. Pastor Honeay was called to the ministry at the age of fifteen and attended Franklin College and the Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. He talks about the differences in morality, family life, and child discipline today compared to his childhood. He discusses the different sects of the Christian church in Spencer and their relationships. He talks about his involvement in local politics and local activism. Finally, he speaks of the decline of the family unit, which he feels is largely due to a decrease in church membership.
  minister; Brown County, Indiana; Monrovia, Indiana; business monopolies; charismatic Christian movement; child discipline; divorce; economic class differences; elder care; Great Depression; high school curriculum; local politics; religious beliefs; school consolidation; theft; World War II; Franklin College; Southern Baptist Theological Seminary
- Hunter, Larry; Hunter, Jan, August 1, 1975; 75-067; Fenton, Leslie; 21 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 50 minutes; no index
  Jan and Larry Hunter have lived in Spencer, Indiana for the past five years. They compare the small town community in Spencer to that of Bicknell, Indiana where they both were raised. The Hunters discuss the educational system in Spencer, where Larry is a high school teacher and Jan is a substitute teacher. They discuss their religious beliefs and the values they hope to teach their children.
  high school teacher; Bicknell, Indiana; local scandal; religious beliefs; Indiana University; Owen Valley High School
- Kay, Oran, November 21, 1974; 74-027; Hatfield, David; Noland, Craig; 23 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 55 minutes; no index
  Oran Kay, born August 9, 1894 and died November 5, 1976, talks about his experiences in Owen County as a general practitioner for forty years. Amongst his accomplishments in his life, he delivered over 6,000 babies. Dr. Kay talks about the changes he has observed in Spencer over the years, including increased crime rates, more divorce, and children moving to other towns to make their living instead of remaining in Spencer. He talks about his practice and the changes he has seen in the medical profession over the years. Finally, Dr. Kay discusses his religious beliefs and how they relate to his interests in medicine.
  physician; Freedom, Indiana; charismatic Christian movement; crime rates; economic class differences; Great Depression; medical profession; Presbyterian Church; religious beliefs; universal health care; Indiana State University; Indiana University
- Kinney, Paul, 1975; 76-005; Noland, Craig; Perry, Robert; 20 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 50 minutes; index
  Paul Kinney, was raised in southern Indiana and spent the majority of his childhood in Owen County. He talks about attending a one-room school in Owen County until a larger school was built later. He talks about the path that led him to become a teacher. He compares the educational system and methods of today with those he experienced as a youth. He compares the actions and attitudes of the youth of his childhood with those present in today's society. Finally, he discusses his religious beliefs, the Unitarian Universalist Church, and fundamental Christianity.
  newspaper columnist; teacher; Brown County, Indiana; Christian fundamentalism; economic class differences; juvenile delinquency; one-room schools; religious beliefs; separation of church and state; teaching methods; Unitarian Universalist church
- Koob, Penny, February 11, 1975; 75-051; Fenton, Leslie; Noland, Craig; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 70 minutes; no index
  Penny Koob talks about the history of Spencer, Indiana, life in a small town, and the economic class differences in Spencer, Indiana.
- Laymon, Gladys, October 17, 1974; 74-006; Hatfield, David; 20 pages; 1 reel, 3 3/4 ips, 50 minutes; no index
  Gladys Laymon, born in 1899, discusses her life in Spencer, Indiana. She describes her education, church affiliation, and family life. She discusses her father's influence upon her and his strict household. She also discusses changes in education and the community. She shares her opinions about civic pride and community organizations.
  minister; teacher; Owen County, Indiana; child discipline; civic pride; community activities; community changes; community organizations; education changes; family; Great Depression; Presbyterian Church; Beems; Laymons
- Lewis, Richard; Lewis, Mrs. Richard, January 31, 1975; 75-073; Fenton, Leslie; 29 pages; 1 reel, 3 3/8 ips, 80 minutes; no index
  Mr. and Mrs. Richard Lewis discuss life in Spencer, Indiana and how they came to live in the town. They discuss their educations and the education of their children. They also discuss are local politics, community activities, and the lack of diversity in the community.
  sales representative; Bloomington, Indiana; Dayton, Ohio; Owen County, Indiana; Tulip Park, Illinois; African-American population; church activities; community activities; economic class differences; hardware business; local economy; local employment; local politics; patriotism; phonics; segregation; small town advantages; Indiana University; MacMillan, Herald
- Miller, Joe, November 1974; 74-026; Perry, Robert; Not transcribed; 1 reel, 3 3/4 ips; 35 minutes
  Joe Miller discusses the educational system in Spencer, Indiana. He also describes the interaction of the religious denominations in the area.
  Owen County, Indiana; Education; religious denominations
- Money, Jack; Money, Althea, February 20, 1975; 76-006; Noland, Craig; 25 pages; 1 reel, 3 3/4 ips, 60 minutes; no index
  Jack and Althea Money discuss their lives in Spencer, Indiana. Jack discusses his childhood activities and education. He discusses his father's drug store and its financial difficulty during the Great Depression. Mr. and Mrs. Money also discuss community clubs and activities as well as the educational system in Spencer.
  pharmacist; school principal; teacher; Indianapolis, Indiana; Lawton, Oklahoma; Owen County, Indiana; child discipline; church activities; class structure; community activities; commuting; family business; family changes; family expectations; Great Depression; high school basketball; Presbyterian Church; religious beliefs; school board; school scandal; World War II; Purdue University
- Nelson, Dick, April 30, 1975; 75-072; Brown, Mike; Perry, Robert; 27 pages; 1 reel, 3 3/4 ips, 60 minutes; no index
  Dick Nelson discusses his role in developing the Community Tax Force in Owen County, Indiana. He shares his experience with welfare relief from the township trustee and the federal government. Nelson also discusses the cycle of poverty and the communities' responsibility for indigent relief through taxes.
  county commissioner; township trustee; Coal City, Indiana; Owen County, Indiana; community activism; community tax force; local employment; local government; property taxes; welfare
- Newsom, Jack B., October 23, 1974; 74-028; Perry, Robert; 27 pages; 1 reel, 3 3/4 ips, 60 minutes; no index
  Jack B. Newsom, born 1908, discusses the history of Spencer, Indiana and its current situation. He talks about his education, childhood activities, and community involvement. He discusses his leadership of the Boy Scouts and the young people of Spencer. He discusses the African-American population in Spencer. Newsom also describes religious, political, and community activism.
  butcher; janitor; teacher; Owen County, Indiana; Reading, Pennsylvania; African-American population; childhood activities; church membership; class structure; community activities; education changes; Great Depression; juvenile delinquency; local politics; religious changes; schooling; Boy Scouts of America; John Herron Art Institute; Rexall Drugstore; World Products Company
- Orrell, Alberta, June 4 ,1974; 75-060; Brown, Mike; 14 pages; 1 tape. 3 3/4 ips. 35 minutes; no index
  Alberta Orrell was born July 6, 1896 in Patricksburg, Indiana and died in May 1978 in Spencer, Indiana. She discusses her schooling, and the influence education had on her, which led her to become a teacher. She talks about the differences between teaching methods of the past and present. She speaks of the changes in small town life over the years. Finally, she discusses the large role her family has played in her life.
  teacher; Clay City, Indiana; Patricksburg, Indiana; child discipline; Great Depression; local politics; local religious communities; religious beliefs; small town life; teaching methods; Indiana University
- Parrish, Arthur, October 12, 1974; 74-009; Perry, Robert; 15 pages; 1 tape, 3 3/4 ips, 40 minutes; no index